<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be inquired of, in the first metropoliticall visitation, of the most reuerend father, George, by Gods prouidence, Arch- bishop of Canterbury, and primate of all England in and for the dioces of [blank], in the yeare of our Lord God [blank], and in the fifth yeare of His Graces translation.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Archbishop (1611-1633 : Abbot)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00149</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10147.4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2091</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23020998</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23020998</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26088</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00149)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26088)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1795:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be inquired of, in the first metropoliticall visitation, of the most reuerend father, George, by Gods prouidence, Arch- bishop of Canterbury, and primate of all England in and for the dioces of [blank], in the yeare of our Lord God [blank], and in the fifth yeare of His Graces translation.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Archbishop (1611-1633 : Abbot)</author>
                  <author>Abbot, George, 1562-1633.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by VVilliam Iaggard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1615?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacking all after signature B₃.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the National Library of Wales.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26088:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26088:1"/>
            <p>ARTICLES To be inquired of, in the firſt Metropoliticall viſitation, of the moſt Reuerend Father, GEORGE, by Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, Arch-Bishop of Canterbury, and Primate of all England; in, and for the Dioces of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> in the yeare of our Lord God, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and in the fifth yeare of his Graces Tranſlation.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>HEB DDIEV HEB DDIM</head>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by William Iaggard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:26088:2"/>
            <head>The Tenor of the Oath, to be Miniſtred to the Church-wardens <hi>and Side-men.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOu ſhall ſweare, that you, and euery of you, ſhall duly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and diligently enquire, of all and euery of theſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles giuen you in charge; and that all affection, fauour, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, hope of reward and gaine, or feare of diſpleaſure, or malice ſet aſide; you ſhal preſent all and euerie ſuch perſon, of, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Pariſh, as hath committed anie offence, or made any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault mentioned in theſe, or any of theſe Articles; or which are vehemently ſuſpected or defamed of any ſuch offence or default: Wherein you ſhal deale vprightly and fully; neither preſenting, nor ſparing to preſent any, contrary to trueth: hauing in this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion God before your eyes, with an earneſt zeale to maintaine trueth, and to ſuppreſſe vice. So helpe you God, and the holy Contents of this Booke.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:26088:2"/>
            <div n="church" type="part">
               <head>¶ Concerning the Church, the Ornaments thereof, and the Churches poſſeſſions.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Mprimis,</hi> whether haue you in your ſeuerall Churches and Chappels, the whole Bible of the largeſt volume, and the Booke of Common Prayer, lately ſet forth by his Maieſties authoritie, both fairely and ſubſtantiallie bound: a Font of Stone, ſet vp in the auncient vſuall place: a conuenient and decent Communion Table, with a Carpet of Silke, or ſome other decent ſtuffe, continuallie laide vpon the Table at time of Diuine ſeruice, and a faire Linnen cloath vpon the ſame, at the time of the receiuing of the holy Communion. And whether is the ſame table placed in ſuch conuenient ſort within the chancell or church, as that the Miniſter may be beſt heard in his Prayer and adminiſtration, and that the greateſt number may communicate: And whether is it ſo vſed out of time of Diuine ſeruice, as is not agréeable to the holy vſe of it; and by ſitting on it, throwing Hats on it, writing on it, or is it abuſed to other prophaner vſes: and are the Ten Commaundements ſet vpon the Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end of your church or chappell where the people may beſt ſée and reade them, and other ſentences of holy Scripture, written on the walles like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for that purpoſe?</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Item,</hi> whether haue you in your ſaid church or chappell, a conueni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent ſeat for your Miniſter to read ſeruice in, together, with a comely pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſet vp in a conuenient place, with a decent cloath or cuſhion for tho ſame, a comely large Surplice, a faire Communion cup, with a couer of Siluer, a Flaggon of Siluer, Tinne, or Pewter to put the Wine in, whereby it may be ſet vpon the Communion Table, at the time of the bleſſing thereof, with all other things and ornaments neceſſarie for the celebration of Diuine Seruice, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments? And whether haue you a ſtrong Cheſt for Almes for the poore, with thrée Lockes and Keies, and another cheſt for kéeping the Bookes, and Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Church, and the Regiſter Booke. And whether haue you a Regiſter Booke in Parchment, for Chriſtnings, Weddings, and Buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and whether the ſame be kept in all pointes, according to the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons
<pb facs="tcp:26088:3"/>
in that behalfe prouided? And whether haue you in your ſaide Church or Chancell, a Table ſet, of the degrees wherein by Law Men are prohibited to marry?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether are your Church and Chappels, with the Chancels there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and your parſonage or vicarage houſe, your Pariſh Almes-houſe and Church-houſe, in good reparations: and are they imployed to godly, and their right holy vſes? Is your Church, Chancell, and Chappell decently and comely kept, as well within as without, and the ſeats well maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, according to the 85. Cannon, in that behalfe prouided? Whether your Church-yard be well fenced, and kept without abuſe: and if not, in whoſe default the ſame is, and what the defect or fault is? And whether any perſon haue incroached vpon the ground of the Church-yard, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any perſon or perſons, haue vſed any thing or place conſecated to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe, prophanely or wickedly?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether haue you the Terrier of all the Gleabe Lands, Medowes, Gardens, Orchards, Houſes, Stockes, Implements, Tenements, and portions of Tiths (whether within your Pariſh or without) belonging vnto your parſonage or vicarage, taken by the view of honeſt men in your ſaid Pariſh? And whether the ſame Terrier be laid vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Biſhops Regiſtery, and in whoſe hands any of them are now. And if you haue no Terrier already made in Parchment, you the Church-wardens &amp; Side-men, together with your Parſon or Vicar, or in his abſence, with your Miniſter, are to make diligent inquiry and preſentment of the premiſes, and make, ſubſcribe, and ſigne, the ſaid Terrier, as aforeſaid?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="ministers" type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Miniſters.</head>
               <p n="1">1 VVHether doth your Miniſter, diſtinctly and reuerently ſay Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruice vpon Sundaies and Holidaies, and other daies appointed to be obſerued by the booke of Common Prayer; as Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies, and Fridaies, and the eeues of euery Sunday and Holiday, at fit and vſuall times? And doth your Miniſter duely obſerue the Orders, Rites, and Ceremonies, preſcribed in the ſaid Booke of common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as well in reading publike prayers and the Letany, as alſo in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the Sacraments, ſolemnization of Matrimony, viſiting the ſick, burying the dead, Churching of Women, and all other like Rites and Offices of the Church, in ſuch manner and forme, as in the ſaid Booke of Common prayer hee is inioyned, without any omiſſion or addition. And doth hee reade the Booke of the laſt Cannons once yearely, and weare a Surplice according to the ſaid Cannons?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Doth your Miniſter bid Holidaies and Faſting-daies, as by the
<pb facs="tcp:26088:3"/>
Booke of Common Prayer is appointed? And doth hee giue warning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand to the Pariſhioners, for the receiuing of the holy Communion, as the two and twentith Canon requireth: and whether hee doth admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the holy Communion ſo often, and at ſuch times, as that euery Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioner may receyue the ſame, at the leaſt thrice in euery yeare: whereof once at Eaſter, as by the Booke of Common Prayer is appointed? And doth your Miniſter receyue the ſame himſelfe, on euery day that hee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtreth it to others, and vſe the words of Inſtitution according to the Booke, at euery time that the Bread and Wine is renewed, according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as by the prouiſo of the 21. Canon, is directed: And doth he deliuer the Bread and Wine to euery Communicant ſeuerally, Whether hee hath admitted to the holy Communion, any Offender or Schiſmaticke, contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to the 26. and 27. conſtitutions, or receyued any to the communion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not of his owne Cure, or put any from the communion, who are not publickly infamous for any notorious crime? Doth he vſe the ſign of the croſſe in Baptiſme, or baptize in any Bazon, or other veſſell, and not in the vſuall font, Or admit any Father to be God-father to his owne childe, or ſuch which haue not receyued the holy Communion, or baptize any Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that were not borne in the pariſh, or wilfully refuſe to Baptize anie Infant in his pariſh, being in danger, hauing béene enformed of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſaide childe: and whether the childe dyed through his defaulte without Baptiſme?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether hath your Miniſter married any without a King, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Banes publiſhed thrée ſeuerall Sundayes or Holydayes in time of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruice, in the ſeuerall Churches or Chappels of theyr ſeuerall abode, according to the Booke of common Prayer, or in times prohibited, albeit the Banes were thrice publiſhed, without a Licenſe or diſpenſation from the Archbiſhop, the Byſhop of the Dioceſſe, or his Chancellor, firſt obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in that behalfe? Or not betwixt the houres of eight and twelue in the forenoone, or haue maried any in any priuate houſe, or if the parties be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the age of 21. yeares, before their parents or gouernors haue ſignifyed their conſent vnto him?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Doth he refuſe to bury any, which ought to be interred in Chriſtian buriall, or defer the ſame longer then hee ſhould, or burie any in Chriſtian buriall, which by the conſtitutions of the Church of England, ought not to be ſo interred?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Is your Miniſter a preacher allowed? If yea, then by whom. If not Whether doth he procure ſome who are lawfully licenſed, to preach month<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly amongſt you at the leaſt?</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26088:4"/>6 Doth your Miniſter (being licenced,) preach vſually according to the Cannons, either in his owne Cure, or in ſome other Church or Chappell neare adioyning, where no Preacher is, and how often he hath béene neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in that behalfe, and doth he Preach ſtanding, and with his Hat off? Or whether doth he or his Curate vpon euery Sunday, when there is no Sermon, reade an homilie, or ſome part thereof, according as hee ought to doe: or in caſe hee be not licenſed to Preach, doeth hee take vppon him to preach or expound the Scriptures in his owne Cure, or elſewhere: If ſo, then you are to preſent the ſame, the time and place, when, and where hee did it.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Doth your Miniſter vſe to pray for the Kings Maieſty, King Iames, and for the Quéenes Maieſty, the Prince, and all their Royall Progeny, with addition of ſuch ſtile and Titles as are due to his Highneſſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort the people to obedience to his Maieſtie, and all Magiſtrates in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie vnder him?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Is your Miniſter continualy reſident vpon his Benfice, and how long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time hath he béen abſent, &amp; in caſe he be licenſed to be abſent: whether doth he cauſe his Cure to be ſufficiently ſupplied, according to the Cannons: or in caſe he hath another Benefice, whether doth he ſupply his abſence by a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſufficiently licenced to preach in that Cure where he himſelfe is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident. Or otherwiſe, in caſe the ſmalneſſe of the Liuing cannot finde a Preaching Minſter, doth he Preach at both his Benefices vſually?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Doeth your Miniſter or Curate, ſerue any more Cures then one: If yea, then what other Cure doeth hee ſerue, and howe farre are they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Doeth your Miniſter euery Sunday and Holliday, before Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Prayer, for halfe an houre or more, examine and inſtruct the youth and ignorant perſons of his Pariſh, in the Tenne Commandements, Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Beliefe, and in the Lordes Prayer, and the Sacrament, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as it is preſcribed in the Catechiſme, ſet foorth in the Booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer?</p>
               <p n="11">11 Doth your Miniſter in the Rogation dayes, goe in perambulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the circuit of the Pariſh, ſaying and vſing the Prayers, Suffrages, and Thankſgiuing to God, appoynted by Lawe, according to his duty, thanking God for his bleſſings, if there be plenty on the earth: Or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to pray for his grace and fauour, if there be a feare of ſcarſity?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Hath your Miniſter admitted any Woman, begotten with child in adultry or Fornication, to be Churched without licenſe of the ordinary?</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26088:4"/>13 Hath your Miniſter or any other Preacher, baptized children, churched any woman, or miniſtred the holy Communion in any priuate houſe, otherwiſe then by Law is allowed?</p>
               <p n="14">14 Doth your Miniſter, being a Preacher, endeuour and labour di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to reclaime the Popiſh Recuſants in his pariſh from their errors, (if there be any ſuch abiding in your pariſh.) Or whether is your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, ouer conuerſant with, or a fauourer of Recuſants, whereby he is ſuſpected not to be ſincere in Religion?</p>
               <p n="15">15 Hath your Miniſter taken vpon him, to appoint any publique or priuate Feaſts, Prophecies, or exerciſes, not approued by Law, or publike authority, or hath vſed to méete in any priuate houſe or place, with any perſon or perſons, there to conſult howe to impeach or depraue the Booke of common prayer, or the Doctrine or Diſcipline of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: If yea, then you ſhall preſent them all?</p>
               <p n="16">16 Hath your Miniſter ſtayed the publication of any excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or ſuſpitions, or doeth hee euery halfe yeare denounce in his Pariſh church, all ſuch of his pariſh as are excommunicated, and perſeuer therein without ſéeking to be abſolued or doth he wittingly and willingly keepe companie with ſuch as are excommunicate: And hath hee admitted into your church any perſon excommunicate, without a certificate of his abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution from the Ordinary, or other competent Iudge?</p>
               <p n="17">17 Doth your Miniſter carefully looke to the reléefe of the poore, and from time to time call vpon his Pariſhioners to giue ſomewhat, as they can ſpare to godly and charitable vſes, eſpecially when they make their Teſtaments?</p>
               <p n="18">18 Whether your Miniſter or any hauing taken holy Orders, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now ſilenced or ſuſpended, or any other perſon of your knowledge, or as you haue heard, hold any conuenticles, or doth preach in any place, or vſe any other forme of Diuine ſeruice then is appointed in the Booke of Common prayer: If yea, then you are to preſent their names, and with whome?</p>
               <p n="19">19 Whether is your Curate licenſed to ſerue, by the Biſhop of this Dioceſſe, or by any other, and by whome?</p>
               <p n="20">20 Doth your Miniſter vſe ſuch decencie and comelineſſe in his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell, as by the 47. Cannon is enioyned: and is he of ſober behauiour, and one that doth not vſe ſuch bodily labour, as is not ſéemely for his ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and calling?</p>
               <p n="21">21 Is your Miniſter noted or defamed, to haue obtained his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice or his orders, by Symony, or anie other way defamed, to be Symo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacall
<pb facs="tcp:26088:5"/>
perſon, or any way noted to bee a Schiſmaticke, or ſciſmaticallie affected, or reputed to be an incontinent perſon, or doth table or lodge any ſuch in his houſe: or is he a frequenter of Tauernes, Innes, or Ale hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or any place ſuſpected for ill rule: Or is hee a common Drunkard, a common Gamſter, or player at Dice, a Swearer, or one that applieth him ſelfe not at his ſtudy, or is otherwiſe offenſiue and ſcandalous to his func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Miniſtry?</p>
               <p n="22">22 Doth your Preacher or Lecturer read Diuine ſeruice, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Sacraments twice a yeare at leaſt in his owne perſon, according to the Cannons?</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Schoole-Maiſters.</head>
                  <p n="23">23 DOth any in your Pariſh take vppon him to teach Schoole, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Licenſe of the Ordinary, and is he conformable to the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion now eſtabliſhed? And doeth hee bring his Schollers to the Church, to heare Diuine ſeruice, and Sermons? And doth he inſtruct his Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in the groundes of the Religion nowe eſtabliſhed in this Church of England, and is he carefull and diligent to benefit his Schollers in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Pariſh Clearkes and Sextons.</head>
                  <p n="24">24 HAue you a fit Pariſh Clearke, aged twenty yeares at leaſt, of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt conuerſation, able to read and write? Whether are his and the Sextons wages paid without fraud, according to the ancient cuſtome of your Pariſh: if not, then by whome are they ſo defrauded or denyed? By whome are they choſen? and whether the ſaid Clearke bee approued by the Ordinarie? and hath he taken an Oath, as in ſuch caſes is fit and required: and is he diligent in his Office, and ſeruiceable to the Miniſter, and doth he take vpon him to meddle with any thing aboue his Office: as Churching of women, burying the dead, or ſuch like?</p>
                  <p n="25">25 Doth your Clarke or Sexton kéepe the Church cleane, the doores locked? Is any thing loſt or ſpoyled in the Church, through his default? doth he ſuffer any vnſeaſonable ringing, or any prophane exerciſe in your Church? Or doth he (when any is paſſing out of this life) neglect to tole a Bell, hauing notice thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="parishioners" type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Pariſhoners.</head>
               <p n="1">1 VVHether any of your Pariſhioners, béeing ſixetéene yeares of age or vpwards, or others lodging or commonly reſorting to any Houſe within your Pariſh, do wilfully abſent themſelues from your Pariſh-church, vpon Sondayes or Holidaies, at Morning and Euening Prayers? Or who come late to Church, and depart from Church, before
<pb facs="tcp:26088:5"/>
ſeruice be done vpon the ſaid daies? Or who doe not reuerently behaue themſelues during the time of Diuine ſeruice, deuoutly kneeling, when the generall confeſſion of ſins, the Letany, the ten Commandements, and al Prayers and Collects are read, and vſing al due and lowly reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence when the bleſſed Name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt is mentioned, &amp; ſtanding vp when the Articles of the Beleefe are read; or who doe couer their head, in the Church during the time of Diuine ſeruice, vnleſſe it be in caſe of neceſſity, in which caſe they may weare a Night-cap or coyfe? Or who do giue themſelues to babling, talking, or walking, and are not attentiue to heare the word preached, or read: or reading, or praying, during the time afore-ſaid? Whether any of your pariſh being of ſixteen yeares of age or vpwards, doe not receiue the holy communion in your Church thrice euery yeare: whereof once of Eaſter, and whether they do not deuoutly kneele at the receiuing thereof?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether any of your Pariſhioners, being admoniſhed thereof, do not ſend their Children, Seruants, and Apprentizes, to the Miniſter, to be Catechized vpon ſuch Sundaies and Holidaies as are appointed? Or whether any of them doe refuſe to come; or if they come, refuſe to learne thoſe inſtructions ſet forth in the Booke of common prayer.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether any of your pariſh doe entertaine within their houſe, any ſoiourner, common gueſts, or other perſons, who refuſe to frequent Diuine ſeruice, or receiue the holy communion, as afore-ſaid? Preſent their names, their qualities, or conditions.</p>
               <p n="4">4 What Recuſant Papiſts are there in your pariſh? preſent their names, qualities, or conditions? whether keepe they any Schoolemaiſter in their houſe, which commeth not to church to heare Diuine ſeruice and receiue the Communion? What is his Name, and how long hath hee taught there, or elſe where?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whether any of the ſaide Popiſh Recuſants, do labour to ſeduce and with-draw others from the Religion now eſtabliſhed? Or inſtruct their Families or children in popiſh Religion: or refuſe to entertain any eſpecially in place of greateſt ſeruice, or truſt, but ſuch as concurre with them in their papiſtry?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Now long haue the ſaid Popiſh Recuſants abſtained from diuine ſeruice, or from the communion, as aforeſaid?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Is there any in your pariſh that retaine vndefaced, or ſell, vtter, or diſperſe, any popiſh Bookes or Writings, or other Bookes, Libels, or writings of any Sectuaries, touching the Religion, State, or Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Eccleſiaſticall of this Kingdome of England, or keepe any Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:26088:6"/>
of ſuperſtition vncancelled or defaced?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Whether haue you any in your Pariſh, which héeretofore being Popiſh Recuſants or Sectuaries, haue ſince reformed themſelues, and come to Church to heart Diuine Seruice, and receiue the Sacraments: If yea, then who they are? And how long ſince haue they ſo reformed themſelues? And whether they ſtill remaine and abide in that conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Is there any in your Pariſh that refuſe to haue their Children Baptized, or themſelues to receiue the Communion at the hands of your Miniſter, taking exception againſt him, and what cauſes or exceptions doe they alledge; or haue any married Wines refuſed to come to church, according to the Booke of common Prayer, to giue God thankes after their Child-birth, for their ſafe deliuerance? And whether doe any of, or in your Pariſh, refuſe to haue their children Baptized in your pariſh-church, according to the forme preſcribed in the Booke of common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Whether any of your Pariſh hauing a Preacher to their parſon, Vicar, or Cudite, doe abſent themſelues from his Sermons, and reſort to other places to heare other Preachers? Or whether any of your pariſh doe communicate or baptize their Children in any other pariſh?</p>
               <p n="11">11 What perſons within your pariſh, for any offence, contumacy, or crime, of Eccleſiaſticall Conuſance do ſtand excommunicate? preſent their names, and for what cauſe they are excommunicated, and how long they haue ſo ſtood, and what parſon or perſons doe writingly and vſuallie kéepe them company?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Whether any, not being in orders, doe execute any prieſtlie or miniſteriall office, in your Church, Chappell, or Church-yard, and what be their names?</p>
               <p n="13">13 Whether any in your pariſh that hauing héeretofore taken vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the order of Prieſt-hoode or Deacon, hath ſince relinquiſhed the ſame, and liues a Lay-man, neglecting his vocation?</p>
               <p n="14">14 Haue any perſon in your Pariſh, quarrelled, or ſtricken, or v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed any violence to your Miniſter, or haue ſtrucken or quarrelled with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other perſon within your Church or Church-yard, or demeaned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe diſorderedly in the Church, by filthy or prophane talke, or any other lend or immodeſt behauiour? Or haue diſturbed the Miniſter in time of Diuine ſeruice or Sermon, or haue libelled or ſpoken ſlanderous wordes againſt your Miniſter, to the ſcandall of his vocation, or diffamed any of his Neighbours, touching any crime of Eccleſiaſticall conuſance?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26088:6"/>
               <p n="15">15 Whether any of, or in your Pariſh, without conſent of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, or other lawfull authority, haue cauſed any to doe pennance, or to be cenſured or puniſhed for any matter of Eccleſiaſticall conuſance, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Veſtry méetings, or otherwiſe by their owne authoritie? Or haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken any money or commutation for the ſame? Preſent their names that haue done it? And who haue been ſo puniſhed? In what manner, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon what cauſe?</p>
               <p n="16">16 Whether any perſon in your Pariſh, doe exerciſe any Trade or labor, buy or ſell, or keepe open Shoppes or Ware-houſes vppon anie Sunday or Hollidaie by themſelues, their Seruants, or Apprentices, or haue otherwiſe prophaned the ſaide daies, contrarie to the orders of the Church of England? And whether there bee any Inne-kéepers, Ale-houſe-kéepers, Victualers, or other perſons, that permitte any perſons in their Houſes, to eate, drinke, or play, during the time of Diuine Seruice or Sermon, or reading the Homilies in the forenoone or afternoone, vpon thoſe daies?</p>
               <p n="17">17 Whether the fift daie of Auguſt, and the fift daie of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, be kept holie, and thankſ-giuing made to God, for his Maieſties and this States happie deliueraunce, according to the Ordinance in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe?</p>
               <p n="18">18 Whether anie of your Pariſh hold or frequent anie conuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles or priuate Congregations, or make or maintaine anie conſtitutions, agreed vppon in anie ſuch aſſemblies? Or anie that doe write, or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquelie or priuatelie ſpeake againſt the Booke of Common prayer, or any thing therein contained, or againſt anie of the articles of Religion agréed vppon, in <hi>Anno</hi> 1562. or againſt the Kinges Supremacie in cauſes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, or againſt the Oath of Supremacie, or of Allegiance, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the ſame to bee vnlawfull, and not warrantable by the worde of GOD? Or againſt anie of the Rites or Ceremonies of the Church of England now eſtabliſhed? Or againſt the gouernment of the Church of England, vnder the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie, by Arch-Biſhops, Biſhoppes, Deanes, Arch-Deanes and other Officers of the ſame: affirming, that the ſame is repugnant to the Worde of GOD, and that the ſaide Eccleſiaſticall Officers, are not lawfully ordained? Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there bee anie Authours, Maintainers, or Fauourers of Hereſie or Sciſme, or that be ſuſpected to be Annabaptiſts, Libertines, Browniſtes, of the Familie of Loue, or of anie other Hereſie or Sciſme? preſent their names?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26088:7"/>
               <p n="19">19 Whether any in your pariſh haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arried within the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rées by Law prohibited, or any couple in your pariſh being lawfully married, liue apart one from the other, without our ſeparation of the Law, or any that haue beene diuorced, which kéepe company with any other at B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ode or at Boord, and when and where were they married?</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Phiſitions, Surgeons, and Mid-wiues.</head>
                  <p n="20">20 HOw many Phiſitions, Chirurgions, or Mid-wiues haue you in your pariſh? How long haue they vſed their ſeuerall Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or Offices, and by what authority? And how haue they demeaned themſelues therein, and of what skill are they accounted to be in theyr profeſſion?</p>
                  <p n="21">21 Whether do any perſons adminiſter the goods of the dead with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out lawfull authority, or ſuppreſſe the laſt will of the dead? Or are there in your pariſh, any wils not yet prooued, or goods of the dead dying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate) left vnadminiſtred? By authority in that behalfe, you ſhall not faile to preſent; the Executors, and all others faulty therein: and alſo how many perſons being poſſeſſed of any Goods and chattels, haue died within your pariſh ſince the xvii. day of Aprill. 1613.</p>
                  <p n="22">22 Whether any with-hold the ſtocke of the church, or any goods, or other things, giuen to good and charitable vſes.</p>
                  <p n="23">23 Whether your Hoſpitals and Almes-houſes, and other ſuch hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and corporations, founded to good and charitable vſes: and the lands poſſeſſions, and goods of the ſame, be ordered &amp; diſpoſed of as they ſhould be? And do the Maiſters, Gouernours, Fellowes, and others of the ſaide Houſes and corporations, behaue and demeane themſelues, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the godly Ordinances and Statutes of their ſeuerall Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</p>
                  <p n="24">24 Whether haue you any in your pariſh to your knowledge, or by common fame or report, which haue committed Adultery, Fornication, or Inceſt; or any which haue impudently bragged or boaſted, that he or ſhe haue liued incontinently with any perſon or perſons whatſoeuer: or any that hath attempted the chaſtitie of anie woman, or ſolicited anie woman to haue the carnall knowledge of her bodie, or which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly reputed to be common Drunkards, Blaſphemers of Gods holie Name; common Sweaters, common Slanderers of their Neighbours, and ſowers of diſcord, filthy and laſciuious Talkers, Vſurers, fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall perſons, Bawdes, or Harborers of women with childe, which bée vnmarried, or conueying or ſuffering them to goe awaie before they haue made ſatiſfaction to the congregation, or any that hauing
<pb facs="tcp:26088:7"/>
héeretofore béene preſented, or ſuſpected of any the foreſaid crimes, haue for that cauſe departed your Pariſh, and are now returned againe? Or any which haue vſed any inchantments, ſorceries, incan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or witchcrafts, which are not made fellony by the ſtatutes of this Realme, or am which haue committed any periuty in any Eccleſiaſticall Court, in an Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall cauſe, or which haue committed any forgery, punniſhable by the Eccleſiaſticall Lawes, and the procurors and abeitors of the ſaid offences: You ſhall truely preſent the names of all, and ſinguler the ſaid Offendors, and with whome they haue committed the laide offences, in caſe they haue not béene publikely punniſhed to your knowledge for the ſame cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mes?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="churchwardens" type="part">
               <head>Touching the Church-wardens, and Side-men.</head>
               <p n="1">1 WHether you and the Church-wardens, Queſt-men, or Side-men from time to time, doe, and haue done their diligences, in not ſuffering any idle perſon to abide eyther in the Church yard, or Church-porch, in Seruice or Sermon time, but cauſing them eyther to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the church to heare diuine Seruice, or to depart, and not diſturbe ſuch as be hearers there? And whether haue they, and do you diligently ſee the pariſhioners duely reſort to the Church euery Sunday and Holliday and there to remaine during Diuine Seruice and Sermon? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you or your predeceſſors, Church-wardens there, ſuffer any Plaies, Feaſts, Drinkings or any other prophane vſages, to be kept in your church, chappell or church-yards, or haue ſuffered to your and their vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt power and endeuour, any perſon or perſons to be tipling or drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in any Inne or Victuling Houſe in your pariſh, during the time of Diuine Seruice or Sermon, on Sundaies and Hollidaies?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether, and how often haue you admitted any to preach with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your church or chappell, which was not ſufficiently licenſed? And whether you, together with your Miniſter, haue not taken diligent héed and care, that euery of your pariſhioners béeing of ſixtéene yeares of age o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vowards, haue receiued thrice euery yeare, as aforeſaid: and alſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t no ſtranger haue vſually come to your church, from their owne pariſh church?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether haue there béene prouided againſt euery communion, a ſufficient quantity of fiue white bread, and of good and wholeſom wine forthe communicants that ſhall receiue? And whether that wine bée brought in a cleane and ſwéete ſtanding pot of pewter, or of other purer Mettall?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26088:8"/>
               <p n="4">4 Whether were you choſen by the conſent of the Miniſter and the pariſhioners? And haue the late Churchwardens giuen vp a iuſt account for their time, and deliuered to their Succeſſors the Money, and other things belonging to the Church, which was in their hands? And are the Almes of the Church faithfully diſtributed to the vſe of the poore?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="magistrates" type="part">
               <head>Concerning Eccleſiaſticall Magiſtrates and Officers.</head>
               <p n="1">1 VVHether doe you know or haue heard of any payment, compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, or agréement, to, or with any Eccleſiaſtical M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trate Iudge, or Officer, for winking at, or ſparing to puniſh any perſon for any offence of Eccleſiaſticall Conuſance, or for ſuppreſſing or concealing of any excommunication, or any other Eccleſiaſticall Cenſure, of, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any Recuſant, or any other offender in the caſes aforeſaid? what ſumme of Money, or other conſideration hath beene receiued or promiſed, by, or to any of them, in that reſpect, by whom, and with whom?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Hath any perſon within your pariſh, paide or promiſed any ſum of Money or other reward, for comutation of pennance for any crime of Eccleſiaſticall Conuſance? If ſo, then with whom? When, and for what, and how hath the ſame beene imployed?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Are your Eccleſiaſticall Iudges and their ſubſtitutes Maiſters of Artes, or Batchellors of the Lawes at the leaſt, learned and practiſed in the Ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall Lawes: Men of good Life and Fame, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly affected in Religion, &amp; iuſt and vpright in executing their offices? Haue they heard any matter of office priuately in their Chambers, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their ſworne Regiſters, or their Deputies preſence?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Doe you know, or haue you heard, that any Eccleſiaſticall Iudge, Officer, or Miniſter, hath receiued or taken any extraordinary Fées, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> other rewards or promiſes, by any wayes or meanes, directly or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of any perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, either for the graunting of the adminiſtration of the Goods and Chattelles of thoſe that haue died inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, to one before another, or for allotting of larger portions of the goods and chattels of thoſe that haue dyed inteſtate, to one more then to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: or for allowing large and vnreaſonable accounts, made by Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or Adminiſtrators: or for giuing them <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> or diſcharges, without Inuentory or account, to defraude Creditors, Legataries, or thoſe who are to haue portions. And what ſummes of Money doe you know, or haue you heard, that any Eccleſiaſticall Iudge or Officer hath taken out of the ſtate of any dying inteſtate, vpon pretence to beſtow the ſame, in <hi>pios vſus:</hi> and how haue the ſame béene beſtowed?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Hath any Eccleſiaſticall Magiſtrate, Iudge, Officer, or any other, exerciſing</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26088:8"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
